[Music]
hello this is embedded I am Alysia white
here with Christopher white when I say
graphics do you assume I mean a big game
computer what about in embedded systems
this week we'll be talking to Gabrielle
Jakob Oh about embedded graphics and
mqtt home automation have real thanks
for joining us
hi crease another yeah that's going good
I know you have worked at some company
we're not going to talk about with my
husband but how about you give us an
introduction of yourself as though you
were meeting us for the first time at a
technical conference all right my name
is Gabriel or Gabrielle in Spanish I'm
an electronics engineer and I typically
work remotely with US companies usually
in software or firmware development and
lately I've been working for graphics
and systems engineering I thought he
would go on for longer I well let's do
lightning round and we will dig into
more because despite your short
introduction you have done many
interesting things so lightning round we
asked you short questions we want short
answers and if we were behaving
ourselves we won't ask you why and how
and hi and all of that Christopher you
ready yeah Gabrielle sure let's go Star
Wars or Star Trek Star Wars what's the
stuff what's your favorite x window
manager wait up
or Katie what's the I've been using kve
constantly for the last ten years I
wouldn't change it for anything
dinosaur movies are shark movies
dinosaur is the Amazon a river a
bookstore or a tribe of work fierce
women for me it's a bookstore or online
shopping destination see ahead a sales
platform in that in that question but
you just want a statement it's
tightening and I'm a little uncertain
about your answer because when I asked
you about Amazon earlier in the week you
said it was a river
yeah because Amazon doesn't really have
any presence in South America but
anytime I go to the US Amazon is there
probably the first site IPC what color
should a llama be a second what color
should a llama be Oh what color so the
thing is llama means flame in Spanish so
that's why we're talking about it it'd
be enough different colors blue is the
color of a good flame so I'd go with
that do you like to complete one project
or start a dozen I'd like to complete
one project what I actually do is start
at awesome alright that's going to dive
into things graphics when you say
graphics and I know you've done a lot of
different working graphics what do you
what is what does that word really mean
when you're talking about embedded
systems and graphics so graphics means
different things to different people for
and users it means what probably what
they see on screen for designers it
means the way they communicate with
users and for us for more engineers it's
the whole pipeline that goes from assets
to some processing the frame buffer and
to the pixels of the display it's a
little odd because I would never say
I've worked in graphics but I have put
bitmaps into flash and then gotten them
out and put them on the screen yeah
should I be saying oh yeah graphics is
on my resume so when you did that did
you constantly write to the screen
did you worry about doing the minimal
amount of work possible to preserve
battery for example one of that is I
think graphics work in a way yeah I did
all that and I I actually drew a graph
too so it wasn't just splatting things
on the screen I had to worry about
pixels yeah I could put that on your
resume
okay graphics right it's graphics
essentially graphics is usually
expensive for batteries so for embedded
work anything that saves you on drawing
time on redrawing things that you don't
need to draw even if you're just like
moving assets from the flash to the
display that's a fairly complicated
process and definitely worth putting in
your wrist could you go through the
process for us so the center of the
graphics process is what's called a
frame buffer which is a complicated work
for an array in memory a buffer where
the pixel information is going to be and
it's going to be sent to the display
through some mechanism the assets
typically come from a flash storage SD
card depending on the resolution it's
the type of storage that we're going to
have there's going to be some sort of
DMA transfer from the storage to RAM
memory or even directly to the frame
buffer and then there's going to be some
processing than either by the CPU in
what's called software rendering or by a
GPU in what's typically called hardware
accelerated rendering and then that
frame buffer is composed into a frame
and that gets sent to the display at a
certain time
the timing of sending images from the
frame buffer to the display has a little
bit of complexity because the display is
doing it something and the CPU is doing
its own thing and if you don't
coordinate that properly you end up
seeing strange artifacts on screen which
you don't want and that depends on how
much complexity you have in the in the
thing you're displaying if you're doing
something very static then usually don't
worry about that but if you have a lot
of animation or changing data or numbers
then then you get into the complexity of
oh I don't want to update the screen
while I'm still updating the data and
I'm put that I want to put on it for the
next update exactly and that it seems
you have a frame buffer on your LCD and
the micro isn't asked acting as frame
buffer and having to send things every
update yeah so this place typically work
in one of two configurations the
simplest one I afford the display is
basically a mode that emulates what all
CRTs display did which is you have a see
every sync signal and H horizontal sync
signal and pixels and you send stuff to
the screen and that gets reflected
immediately into pixel information and
then an evolution of that is this place
with graphics ran on them where the
microcontroller can send information at
a given time and then that gets
displayed to pixels after a certain
refresh period yes if your data sheet
says you have to use H sink in vsync run
away run away very quickly oh well I
mean you have to often cuz it's cheaper
but it is a lot simpler in the code to
have something that has onboard RAM but
you pay for it in your processor because
you know your processor is doing all of
that everyone knows that freeware is
free so that's why they're typically
used to exchange our complexity for free
or complexity so that's all how you
would deal with like a bear
metal system but you worked on this
thing what's it called
SDL simple directmedia layer which of
course I mean it has the word simple in
it so it should be simple right that's a
it's a nothing but it's it's it's simple
for the user
it's quite simple for the user actually
it's not simple in its implementation
what is it but is it first like if
nobody if somebody hasn't heard of it or
what it what is this little description
so let's say let's let's start with the
simplest case right you have a frame
buffer on our toes and you create your
rendering engine right so you tailor
everything to you tailor everything for
that artists your whole rendering
pipeline is oriented towards having just
one frame buffer that you can't directly
access and everything works nice your
input comes from from interrupts or
whatever then imagine that you want to
port that to with a minimal effort to I
don't know a desktop simulator on
Windows or Mac then all your rendering
functions basically stop working because
Windows uses its own API for rendering
and for window creation and for input
for events etc and Mac uses a different
scheme Linux this is a different scheme
Android doesn't even have a main loop
that you can use so what SDL does is
abstract all of that into a single API
slash application philosophy so instead
of having to worry about how you create
window a window on windows some
background Linux you create you call SPL
underscore create window and everything
is magically so internally you don't
need to worry about how the main loops
of the OS work you don't need to worry
about how to read the keyboard or the
gamepad or the mouse everything comes as
events in this
way across all platforms so it's
basically a harbor and always
abstraction like yeah cutie cute to some
extent but cute is much more it's it's
it's more of an app of total application
framework so it has networking and all
kinds of stuff language extensions
whereas this is this isn't see it's more
directed toward input and graphics do I
have that right so yeah so I don't know
how cutie obstructs platforms internally
but you could have for example cutie a
port that works on top of 50 STL if you
want it like STL provides the per
minimal layer to abstract window
creation input OpenGL context creation
and that's it QT provides a whole bunch
of other stuff okay
how do these relate to like OpenGL and
direct3d so after you create a window if
you want to render using GPU you need
something that's called an OpenGL
context which is basically a way to
reference what you're doing for the hard
work to know that you are the one
issuing instructions and you which text
or euro you own etc so the way you do
that is different on each platform
creating an opportunity is not really
part of the OpenGL specification but a
part of the window manager slash OpenGL
integration so as DL abstracts all of
these and it manages the windows way of
doing it
the egl way of doing it the back way of
doing it and you just have to call SPL
chair clear context or whatever it's
called and you get a context and don't
have to worry about any of the internal
details and it also has a neat way to on
up in OpenGL you need to load the
function pointers from the library if
you don't want to make statically and it
helps you with that as well it's not the
only library that does
this but it's it's a nice utility that
provides how does all of this so I know
you're an expert in STL because I know
you've contributed to it it's an open
source project how does this relate to
embedded systems it doesn't so STL
doesn't really have support for
narratives right so if we equate
embedded systems to having an artists or
not having an artist at all
STL doesn't really apply here but there
are a growing number of small wearables
that use Linux and if you want to for
example develop an app and not have to
download it constantly to the device to
try it
you can develop an SPL app you try it on
the desktop you use the OpenGL ES
graphics stack and what you see on the
desktop is going to be exactly or very
close to what you see on the device and
so that cuts down development time by a
lot
and there are many devices doing Linux
embedded yeah if I wanted to have
something that was doing Linux and was
making graphics I mean I guess you know
when I do embedded Linux I just plug in
an HDMI screen and it all just kind of
works but that's not that's not what
you're talking about let's say can we
consider the Raspberry Pi platform yes
yeah okay so let's say you want to
develop for Raspberry Pi and you don't
want to compile everything on device
because it takes forever yeah yeah so
you cross compile and then once you
cross compile you have to download it to
the Raspberry Pi try it run it try it
with the whatever input you've managed
to connect to the Raspberry Pi and see
what it looks like or what you can do is
that what's basically that same app on
your desktop
peel it right there mess around with the
UI as much as you want and once you're
settled with that you know that STL is
going to abstract most of the
differences in Hauer
because your desktop has a different GPU
and it probably has a different
resolution etc and so you try you send
that which is basically there's pretty
much the same code pinned it on top of
STL and OpenGL ES and that should run on
the Raspberry Pi mostly unmodified so
it's it this doesn't mean that you
cannot develop on the Raspberry Pi
directly or that you shouldn't
it is saves time if especially if you're
doing a complex project it's also nice
to be able to give a simulator to your
designers and say well this is what it's
gonna look like on the thing and then
you don't care if the designers are
using Mac or Windows or Linux and you
still get a reasonable fuck
of what their version of graphics is
gonna look like on the embedded version
of graphics on the device yes and if for
example tomorrow competitor to the
Raspberry Pi show SAP and the software
stack that they provide doesn't have a
window manager but it has direct
hardware access for example most of the
event the GPUs have that so SDL supports
Peapod these GPUs directly and it can
create windows on the directly without
having to go through a window manager so
you your code runs on that it's a
different view it if a whole different
system and you don't have to change
anything for that to work and of course
if you're doing things like games you
support multiple platforms out of the
box with minimal effort you have an
elected the STA one of the things that
people were saying about it was there's
a game engine I'm like I don't think
that's right but it's not it's not a
game engine it's a it's a platform an OS
abstraction layer you you still have to
make your own engine on top of that but
SEO makes it simpler because you can
make a game engine that is mostly
cross-platform so you don't have to
worry about the display systems the
display and the input and many other
things yes sound as well in addition
today you did a database thing with STL
let me see if I've got this right
community sourced database of game
controller map means to be used with STL
to game controller functionality
I don't think all those words go
together so one of the things that SDL
added quite recently or maybe in the
last four years it's a way to abstract
game controllers so if you look at
different game controllers the most
popular ones are the Xbox and
Playstation ones and then there's a
whole myriad of buttons and things that
if you are a game developer for example
and you want to map all of that variety
to something consistent on your game
you're basically facing a titanic task
because you need to know what what
possible things the user may have in
their home and that they let them to use
on your game and map that somehow to the
game one of the most common solutions is
to have some kind of mapping
functionality in the game where it says
okay press the button to jump and you
press something and then that gets
recorded the database that you're
referring to is a way to formalize on
that so as the else supports mapping of
many controllers to an Xbox controller
format and people around the world have
been contributing those mappings that
they do with the controllers that they
get their hands on and we aggregate all
of that into this database so once when
anyone wants to ship a game and support
a whole bunch of controllers besides the
ones that still supports out of the box
which is fairly minimal amount they load
up this database and they can support I
don't know the last time I checked it
was like 300 computers mentally I have
this pictured as though it was I was
using code composer and switched out the
key bindings to match my Visual Studio
code is that is that a good mental model
or is that yes totally do it okay that's
it that's exactly what it is yes the
mental model of somebody doesn't play
enough games that's true or place with
keyboard and mouse no I had the VR
system and play with my feet so this
database thing and the STL things you do
and it's all open source and how do you
get paid you don't it's it's an
investment basically so the story is
that I started with some friends try to
make a game and to make a game of course
the first thing that they tell you is if
you're making a game don't make your own
nature so what did we do
we started making of course the end the
action was
SDL and I still had a number of
shortcomings that were angry on me so I
start to contribute in there and sings
one singlet to another and ended up
working on company in the u.s. that
basically found me through my open
source contributions the the reason why
I did those contributions is to learn
and also to get some recognition or two
it's it's a way to build up your resume
when you don't have specific expertise
in the area that you want to work in
probably so yeah it's a there's a lot of
paid open-source development but I
haven't been a button that it's been
everything is being voluntary for me
cool awesome listener question some of
which you've seen because you're in our
slack Channel let's see how about secret
is out many people are in our slack
Channel and if you want to be in our
slack channel in your listener all you
have to do is contribute a buck or two
on patreon and then you get the link in
then you can say hello
okay so Nick Nick asked Nick the
exploding lemur asked if you have any
tips for hunting down processors with
stable graphics drivers and/or easily
acquired graphics engine specs and open
drivers so the state of GPU drivers is
very bad the only ones I know of that
open source and quite good actually at
the Raspberry Pi one which is I think a
work in progress and then on desktop you
have the Intel works besides that
everything is be behind three layers of
DRAM and NDA's and Chris knows about
this you talk to one vendor and they
talk to the other vendor and you finally
get to the one that sells the GPU IP and
nobody gives you any internal details
unless
probably talking from VP to VP level
it's very complicated of course they're
doing super-secret stuff so I can
understand I'm not sure no it's all the
same
what about below that I mean that's
that's GPU stuff but in the
microcontroller world there's not a lot
of for hobbyists or people you know
doing like thinking about a Kickstarter
project there's not a lot of devices
that help out much with graphics no kind
of a 2d space yeah I've seen a couple of
SD chips that have a 2d accelerator
which is essentially a DMA engine that
can do like to the transfers where you
can specify an area and copy it to
another area and a bit more about them
that is an engine that can do scaling
and maybe rotation in 2d but that's
pretty much it if the other issue with
this kind of implementations is that
they're very a doc so each manufacturer
does their own thing and there's
absolutely no standards and maybe many
of those implementations are not very
distributed so expect plenty of bugs if
you're doing that and it's a huge
security risk in a way because you're
moving data around behind the CPU
protection mechanisms so you can easily
shoot yourself in the foot when you talk
about moving data into frame buffers and
being able to scale it some of that has
to do with fonts and having a font in
flash and then moving it to the screen
or having a letter in flash and moving
it to the screen because the font is a
series of letters how do you how do you
deal with fonts do you have a favorite
font do you prefer to do vectors and and
take the computing overhead do you
usually use bitmap fonts what do you
want to do so
yeah vector phones are ideal they
usually cost you just a little bit above
what you can spend on systems mostly
because they hover around a hundred K
and I have the case probably just
outside of your budget in many embedded
systems it's basically a compression
mechanism right you have the vectors in
a in a file and when you want to render
something you tessellate these vectors
into a bitmap and gosh that probably
somewhere and use that so if you are
using bitmap fonts what you're doing is
most of the same process butterfly yeah
you start from a font and you render the
bitmaps and you store only the bitmap on
your flash memory the issue with that is
that you cannot really change your text
size and you need to have space to store
all of the glyphs that you want to
render which if you're supporting things
like Chinese for example it's not a
trivial amount of space I think most of
the cortex-m processors can render
TrueType fonts correctly if you have the
run so if you have above I say 256 K of
nori you should probably give two type
fonts ago there is it's work with very
easy to work with
see how he's heard if they were really
hard kind of avoided them you need a
library yeah you you've got to
open-source libraries free type and STP
to type which is actually one of those
single feather priests like so much so
you just use that and it gives you
whatever you want okay good question
from Ben which was initially phrased why
do the displays that the gas-station
take five years to update for every key
press and then was changed to what are
some common mistakes made during
embedded graphics
I mean that 35 or 40 more minutes
mqtt tears right last time the I think
the thing that people don't understand
the the most common misunderstanding
about graphics is that graphics is a
bandwidth about operation right you you
do have some CPU processing and GPU
processing but the first limit that
you're going to hit is going to be the
bandwidth limit because it's mostly
about transferring information so in the
case of very slow displacing gas
stations or ATMs or whatever what
usually happens is that they choose a
processor for price reasons or business
reasons or whatever and then they make a
totally separate decision about the
resolution based on what this place they
can get or what resolution but visual
impact they want to have on the user and
then those things are completely
separate and they usually don't match up
and then that's why you end up with
those ugly low frame rates that you
could you say this is one of the reasons
that we do when we talk about DMA when
we talk about graphics because it is all
about moving things from here to there
as fast as possible and still being able
to do other stuff yep
are there other common mistakes
the other common mistake which is
related to probably one of the other
questions that I saw on the slab channel
is across products
the resolution is evaluated as a new
thing all the time so you change
products and you change completely the
resolution because again business
reasons or reliability or whatever and
then you start on your second product
you start maintaining two sets of assets
which don't really mesh with each other
and on the server iteration you start
handling three types of aspect ratios
and it all gets complicated so one if I
could make a choice across an entire set
of products I'd say stick to the same
resolution or at least stick to the same
aspect ratio that's a hard problem even
when you're not doing you know a small
embedded system that's even if you're
doing something with Linux or Apple's
had this problem right oh we came out
with a new phone and now all the
developers have to go and regenerate
everything and there's no good way to
make this automatable because things
don't look good when they're scaled or
when they're automatically laid out so
yeah it's a big problem every time when
you look at movies I mean you have
different scaling on whether whether
you're watching it on TV with the black
bars or whether you're in the movie
theater or whether you're watching an
old movie or a new movie the aspect
ratio and resolution that's just a
never-ending problem yep
and trying to decouple it in your code
is a great idea but as Chris said you it
looks different so you can't just say oh
we're gonna pound F that out it's not it
doesn't work like that yeah so there's a
few techniques that came mostly from
their web development work because web
the web pages are subject to a bunch of
resolutions and they need to look from
this basically what's the same set of
assets and code they need to look the
same
roughly the same so there are techniques
to minimize that but they cost in terms
of treatment development and CPU
processing power so they're not always
feasible on about systems well it's gone
and talked about mqtt because there were
some questions about that and I heard
you have been doing some home automation
yes though I must warn you that mqtt is
so great that I'm willfully ignorant of
all its internal implementation details
I enjoy it as an end user mostly what is
it it's a communications protocol
typically associated to IOT devices
it runs on tcp/ip and it follows
publication subscription principles ok
so you've already said tcp/ip and I'm
like oh I'll just take out all my micros
because that's that's heavy weight to
start with and then this is on top of it
it's the Internet of Things if you don't
have PCP IP you're just a thing I'm okay
with that that's a there's a there's a
variant that I'm not really familiar
with that doesn't run on top of tcp/ip
but I mean we're talking something that
can do at least Wi-Fi or Ethernet and
cover tcp/ip stack okay so it's it's on
top of tcp/ip
so guarantee transmissions as long as
you have the path between them and
publish/subscribe so your widget your
IOT thing probably publishes the data
and then some server like things
subscribes how does how does it work
so there's you need to have one broker I
use mosquito there's a bunch of them
which is like the half the central point
of the MQTT network and everything else
is a client and each client can
subscribe or publish information the
processes you
something with a topic and a payload and
the other clients can subscribe to a
topic and when you publish to that topic
take at the payload that you transmit it
it's here to stores IOT devices so the
whole my device went offline expecting
you have messages for availability so
whenever you come online you say I'm
available and whenever the broker sees
that you've gone offline because you
don't respond it's automatically a
message saying this device is offline it
also retains miss the broker can retain
messages so for example if you want to
talk to a thermostat and have a
temperature setting you publish I don't
know ABF I want to set into the ADF and
retain that
so whenever the thermostat comes back
online the broker communicates that
information automatically and the other
piece of technology that it has is a QoS
setting a quality of service which says
if you want the message to be
transferred once or if you really want
to make sure that the message is
received by our clients okay so mosquito
is the broker and it is sort of the hub
yes what do you run that on do you have
like a home server or are you running
that annika Raspberry Pi sort of thing
so at home I have a has a ou
distribution which is a home assistant
Bistro that runs with the Raspberry Pi
it's center around containers and on one
of the containers you run mosquito and
everything talks to that and home
assistant talks to that as well so
everything connects through the
Raspberry Pi what do you have for the
devices Oh devices it's mostly
esp8266 no that's you for the doors and
lights that kind of thing did you say
node
nah yeah it's called now them Co so I
click like Inc like it now you know it's
called no then see you and it out of the
box it grants Louis oh nothing make
sense okay what are you building with
this we knew and when I first heard of
this you were gonna do like one little
thing yeah I had a greenhouse
temperature control now I have two doors
lights the home alarm and the heating
system of the house connected there it's
pretty neat because you program
everything in micro Python or if you
doing something a bit more intensive you
use platform i/o we know framework and
it's just plug and play mostly it's very
satisfying way of working I don't even
know how you install the tool change for
this
everything is click click click click
here and everything works perfectly
it's amazing what about power I mean if
you're alarming if you're alarming doors
if you have door alarms don't those just
run on batteries and the esps are ok but
they're not like long-term batteries the
USB for the alarm is connected to the
alarm battery which is like a huge brick
that can last a few days
yeah that's no issue and also being
worrying about battery life for 4 years
old I don't care anymore
[Laughter]
MQTT comes in flavors do you have to
worry about any of that or does it all
just kind of poof works it magically
works yeah I I don't think there's
versioning at least
so since I'm building everything
basically from the say saying source
code everything works
I know if I bring a binary from
somewhere else into my home automation
which doesn't seem like a the best idea
in the world probably won't work
I don't
how it manages versioning you make this
sound very easy it's surprisingly easy
yeah on Python you just create a client
and issue MQTT that subscribe to
subtopic and you start getting call
backs for that that's what you have to
do it's three lines it's funny as you
talk about the architecture of it with
the publish and subscribe and the broker
and it sounds very much like robot
operating system okay but going on going
on to the next subject of my long list
of things to ask a Gabrielle about where
are you based
I'm in Argentina in a city called Mar
del Plata 400 kilometres south of Buenos
Aires on the coast and I have met you in
person near San Francisco how many hours
did you have to travel to get San
Francisco so there's no direct flights
to San Francisco from Argentina
and there's no definitely no direct
flights from foreign to anywhere from my
city so I had to take a bus to what
Osiris and then you typically go to LA
if you're lucky and then from there to
SF or San Diego
so it's about 20 hours 22 hours if
you're lucky I see you don't commute
regularly no my communities from my bed
to my desktop how do you how do you
handle that I have is working remotely
for you and and how do you make it work
and not distraction though I mean it's a
nice deal it's not easy to get started
doing this it it it has all the
challenges of working at home focus of
doing the things - especially working in
Hardware pinyon Argentina the hair needs
to be shape in its go through customs
that's a whole ordeal and
and the companies that you work with
need to be remote oriented in a way they
to be prepared to have remote workers
cut the philosophy required to do that
but that's probably not different from
the work that you do there right being
about hundred kilometres or a thousand
or ten thousand is the same in terms of
human interaction the things that get
more complicated is when you jump across
countries and you're doing horrible
projects I started doing software
projects basically web development
initially because it's much easier to
work like that against the server on the
Amazon Cloud Data Brazil buddy Seattle
that if if you depend on hard work that
maybe breaks and you need to wait a week
or two to get a replacement work do you
have any advice for people who want to
work remotely in general and then do you
have any advice review who went to work
remotely internationally like you're
doing I think the the first thing if you
want to work for example from Argentina
for US companies it's just get started
just make an account on freelance or
Elance or oDesk or whatever it's called
now and just get cheeks doing PHP or
JavaScript work and it's going to pay
very loudly just do that for some time
to get used to working remotely the
you're not going to get the most amazing
jobs doing that but you're going to
create a resume and and work that you
can point to maybe more interesting
employers saying to them basically I'm
responsible I can manage my own time and
I can get things done and then after
that is the same as for any work you
need to establish relationships with
people and people need to know you know
what you can do and if you cannot get
into an area that you
then look for open-source projects that
you can contribute to as a way to prove
that you can get the work done there any
other pitfalls that you've come across
just in terms of mechanics of things
like shipping I know that sometimes
shipping Hardware can be a pain because
it gets either confiscated or stuck in
customs are there ways to to suggest to
the companies you work for to smooth
those things over or is that just kind
of constituting business yeah in
Argentina in particular FedEx is the can
we advertise companies yeah FedEx please
send us a check yeah exactly let's let
give us a couple of three shipments it's
the best way to send things they
typically take a week to get stuff here
and it usually doesn't get bothered by
customs if you stay within the courier
weight and price limits and then if you
go beyond that then you start getting
issues right but that's that's like a
logistics problem that it's it's not
really in your hands to to solve to do
anything about I say that the most
difficult thing working probably
probably for you is the same is getting
people to acknowledge you and keep you
in the loop on things that's the when
you're not physically present talking
face to face to people the relationship
changes especially when there's a time
zone change yeah so if you can visit in
person every now and then that smooth
things watched you and I found that
working remotely has helped with some
jobs my lab is pretty good compared to
many of the startups I work with my
office is extraordinarily quiet compared
to many of the offices I visit and when
I work remotely we get better at
documentation part of that's just cuz I
document things and I like to and I
liked
have them documented because I like to
forget things very quickly and the
documents help me but also the documents
help them whether they realize that or
not I realize it when somebody emails me
from a client I worked on two years ago
and says I thought this would be
impossible and then I Richard document
realized I only had to uncomment like
one line and it was all good and I mean
that sort of thing is awesome also you
cannot not if you're working on office
is not true yeah
so if you're not feeling well if you
feel like you're blocked by a problem
exists you're to just get up and take a
walk or whatever in your head and come
back concentrate on on the problem
really think it through the speciality
OpenOffice plants that have become
typically in the US are very distracting
it's at least for me personally mostly
because I'm not used to them it cuts by
productivity a lot I totally agree and
working as a consultant being able to
clock out and go for a walk it's just so
valuable yeah because it also benefits
the company because your brain really
doesn't stop processing the what you're
doing but you can really build for
taking a walk at least I don't may be
shocked but when you're doing that
you're really thinking the problem that
you're facing the background yes very
much yes yes going back to graphics
Chris you had another couple questions
there was one in the list here that I
thought I think we skipped over that was
kind of the crux of the difficulty of
graphics on embedded systems and that's
if you're doing something moderately
complicated the dance between updating
the frame buffer syncing
updating the screen I just like to talk
about that a little bit to give people a
sense for okay if you really want to do
something that maybe has animation
that's fluid and doesn't have tearing
heart effects how you go about
architecting your system first you have
to describe what tearing me Oh
tearing would be so if you if you're
updating your frame buffer out of sync
with how the display is perhaps reading
it out you might have half of your
screen updated in the frame buffer and
half old data and then the display might
read it out and put it on the display
and then you tap this half updated
screen which since oftentimes you're
moving something it would look like
you've got a big tear mark aligned
across the screen so how do you solve
that right it's a I don't know if we
can't reveal this grease but it's a an
ancient secret passed from generation to
generation of super engineers and it's
called double buffering yes sorry I I
gave it out I'm sorry
I'm going to return my trimmer engineer
patch so what you do typically is you
have instead of only one frame buffer if
you can afford it you have two three
buffers of the displayed resolution and
while you're building your frame with
the CPU or the GPU on one you are
displaying the another one on the screen
and to switch between the frame buffers
what you do is you wait for a signal
from the display which is most likely
the missing signal which indicates that
the display has started scanning the
frame buffer so once it started scanning
the frame buffer it will read from the
active frame buffer all the pixels and
the pixels that it has read it will no
longer be they will no longer be in use
so that's the moment where when you can
switch frame buffers and the active one
becomes the back in the back buffer and
you can start drawing your new frame
there when the display that's seeing
with the front buffer and so this is a
ping pong buffer system where
when ping is activated is in use by the
LCD you write to the pong buffer and
then you wait for the signal to say to
swap and then the pong buffer is being
used by the LCD and you write to the
ping buffer yes and if you've got to
just play with an embedded frame buffer
usually they only have enough on there
for one frame right they don't have
double buffering so you might have to
add at least another buffer in your RAM
well how does that work sometimes you
can use you you can't always read out
the LCDs frame buffer that's usually
kind of exciting too
and so you have to keep a shadow of what
they write right it's usually very slow
to read the frame buffer in the display
itself so when the reason comes you send
the active frame buffer in a one-way
mode and start working with the
information that you had on that frame
buffer then there are tricks if your
performance is not enough hour you don't
have enough memory space for two frame
buffers you do like partial updates of
different buffers so you try to minimize
the amount of pixels that you change and
then maybe you can get it fast enough to
draw the frame rate that you want to
draw out maybe not 60 Hertz but maybe
thirty and without seeing the
disturbances of the screen do you have
any test methodologies when I had to do
LCD graphics system I found later that I
wished I had better unit tests to start
with involving lines and squares and do
you have a good way to figure out if you
have written your graphic system
correctly it's very hard to test I I
wish I had a solution for that usually
graphics have some form of user input
involvement so yeah there are dinner
thankfully import ways of testing things
but and I I couldn't of volunteer a
solution
now usually you accumulate a series of
visual tests and you can run through it
it's basically recordings of all of the
errors that you have had to deal with I
mean you start out with this is what I
think you know this test this
functionality and it looks good
but you forget some corner case or
usually it's an actual corner exactly so
you had update the test and so you end
up with a suite of things that you can
do but like Gabrielle said it's very
hard to automate that because it's a
visual thing so I mean you can kind of
take screenshots and compare them
against known good results but that's
all very painful yeah it's a tough
problem I remember writing the word red
and green and blue in each color and
then realizing I hadn't written them in
the correct colors because I wasn't sure
which was orangey and B on my display
but that's a classic problem mixing up
the components orders yeah yeah when you
have black and white which a lot of
times you start out with black and white
it doesn't matter but then when you
start doing animations for your team
suddenly it's important that red is red
and not green well here's a question for
you that the folks on the Select might
have asked but they didn't there's a lot
of different display technologies out
right now and if your decide if you're
building a hobby project or starting
some small product it might not be clear
what the best thing to choose is there's
there's OLED there's LCD there's other
things matrix lights are actually pretty
popular right now Inc and there's
there's drawbacks to all of these right
to list the tropics yeah yeah the
drawbacks of OLED because that may be
important to me soon oh that's a yeah
that's a pet peeve of mine so let's type
in time
they're like little gnomes that emit
light and they get older and older each
time you make them make
photos and the more you make them emit
photons the more they die the more
quickly they die so yeah that's a fun
fact that I wasn't aware of when I
started working with all it this place
and people I could choose them because
they're super bright and and you know
the monochrome ones look really really
engaging but really we're just killing
little-known murdering yes that's
scientifically proven - yeah in a
microscope just enable kamikaze mode and
you'll see they're very bright but the
nice thing about all that is you don't
draw a power your power draw is
proportional to how many pixels you're
actually lighting right yeah so each
each so each pixel is like an individual
light instead of being the LCD system
where you have a backlight and you're
basically filtering the backlight to
produce colors so the contrast is the
contrast appearance is much nicer
because the black is really black this
there's no light coming what the black
pixels and then color I've heard the
gnomes die at different rates yeah blue
dice especially fast not sure why
they're probably much larger because we
perceive blue with lower intensity so to
produce the same perceived blue-green
for example brightness the the blue one
needs to make much more effort my story
is that we haven't had blue LEDs for
that long so we're just not really good
at making them yeah that's true
or maybe the other pixels don't like
blue yeah those no hate theater no yeah
so yeah so so they give you these curves
and they say if your Sultanate's
this display can live for 100 hours and
then what you get is a
a pixel that doesn't isn't able to
emitter at its fullest and depending on
what you're showing screen you can get
burning a burning effect which is an
image that seems to be constantly there
and that's produced by the lack of the
pixels to do a bit light at the same
level that the neighboring pixels can
with it I mean that that wouldn't that
sounds fine not not really not at all
fine okay so so OLED is see if you
manage if you manage to get all the
knobs to die at the same rate that makes
fine because you won't notice it for for
very long time
the problem is when they start dying at
different rates for me a pattern then
you really notice them okay so LEDs
might be an option but those are very
power inefficient so I guess LCDs those
are fine they've been around for a long
time they must work right yeah ago the
problem is if you if you want to make a
really nice-looking device with no
borders around it it's very hard to do
with LCD because they require a plodding
area somewhere so you get that if you
look at wearable devices with LCDs you'd
see that some where they may be
advertised a ride over on a region
because they cannot avoid having that
section then it has the backlight issue
you have to there's all very few LCDs
that you can see that they have trans
reflective one switch light coming into
it is reflected off a substrate on the
back and then and then you can see it
daylight but usually you have to have
some sort of light emitting thing on the
back and that's usually some white LEDs
or some phosphorescent thing fluorescent
thing which draws a lot of power so I
should use ink you should use beeps
Morse code I do feel like we're gonna
get down to like you just shouldn't have
it display at all you can avoid it it's
a big part of the power budget if you
want the display just watch the TV all
right do we have more graphics questions
that was the main one I wanted to go
back to I don't think we missed an
analyst well I mean the list is just
there because I have to do something for
the show other than talk yeah well I
have lots of questions for Gabriel but
he's not going to answer them I think
I've already gone over the line with a
double buffer and the nobs thing I don't
think I should have revealed that okay I
have one more question for you that when
you were young when you were the age
that your sons are now yes what did you
want to be when you grow up yeah I
wanted to be an engineer really from
that young yes so before I wanted to be
in a chair I actually wanted to be a
garbage collection man also buy boxes
but right after that I wanted to be at
my my my stepdad was a garbage
collection person and I you know in high
school I was like oh god don't tell
anybody to say he drives trucks and I
found out a few years ago that I was the
coolest person in the neighborhood to
the five-year-old who lived across the
street when he found out that my stepdad
Drive garbage trucks he was just like
that was the coolest thing yeah I was
probably the same yeah but you but you
knew what an engineer was and you wanted
to build things at a young age did you
take things apart my Iancu was an
electronics is an electronics engineer
so I guess that's what I picked that up
from yeah I absolutely was hated by my
brothers I constantly took apart toys
and I never put them back together no
once you know how they work they don't
who cares yeah my mom says that I went
to the University so I could learn how
to put the toys well I think we've kept
you for long enough Gabrielle do you
have any thoughts you'd like to leave us
with yes I'd like to read you a quote
one of my favorite it says it's from
Douglas Adams from mostly harmless and
it says a common mistake that people
make when trying to design something
completely foolproof is to underestimate
the ingenuity of concrete faults yes a
lesson to live by yeah I guess it has
been Gabrielle Okubo software
electronics and systems engineer at
large you can contact him via Twitter
via his webpage which will of course be
in the show notes or you can email us
and we will forward it along thank you
so much for being with us Gabrielle
thank you
it's been very nice being here thank you
to Christopher for producing and
co-hosting and of course thank you for
listening
you can always contact us at show at
embedded FM or hit the contact link on
the embedded FM website where you can
also find at the blog and now a quote to
leave you with a from a jorge luis
borges plant your own gardens and
decorate your own soul instead of
waiting for someone to bring you flowers
embedded is an independently produced
radio show that focuses on the many
aspects of engineering it is a
production of logical elegance an
embedded software consulting company in
California if there are advertisements
in the show we did not put them there
and do not receive money from them at
this time our sponsors are logical
elegance and listeners like you
you